<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration against the crosse petition wherein some secret letts of the intended reformation are discovered, the danger of division prevented, and the unitie of this iland in religion urged / by the Commissioners of the Generall Assembly.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37323</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8631154</idno>
  <idno type="VID">41505</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248498212</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28588</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08631154</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37323)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41505)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1255:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration against the crosse petition wherein some secret letts of the intended reformation are discovered, the danger of division prevented, and the unitie of this iland in religion urged / by the Commissioners of the Generall Assembly.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41505:1"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION AGAINST THE CROSSE PETITION:</p>
            <p>WHEREIN Some secret letts of the intended Reformation are discovered. The danger of Division prevented. And The Unitie of this Iland in Religion urged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> THE COMMISSIONERS OF THE GENERALL ASSEMBLY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings most excellent Majestie. 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:41505:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41505:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He word of GOD, the example of the People of GOD, and of the Kirk of Christ, since the beginning, and our own late, but very notable and never to be forgotten experience, may abundantly teach us, that the motions, resolutions and endeavours of the Godly, for the advancement of the Kingdome of the Son of GOD, by establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or propagating the Reformation of Religion, must meet with a world of opposition and hinderances, which might make their hearts to faint, and their hands to fail, if upon the same grounds and documents they were not taught to acquit themselves, in doing the dutie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them by the necessitie of their callings, and for the successe to depend upon the unsearchable wisedome, and invincible power of GOD, which are made perfect in the simplicitie and weaknesse of his servants: <hi>The Zeal of the Lord of hosts will performe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There hath ever been in the Kirk of Christ, and shall be to the end, a generation which maketh more accompt of the World, then of the Faith of Christ, doth conceive that differences about Religion are but the contentions of Kirk-men, that therefore there is no necessitie of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion, and that to know nothing of this kinde, is the surest Faith, and seeketh in their service to Kings and Princes civilly to supererogate at their hands, beyond the deservings of others, and above the expressed desires and commands of Princes themselves, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of their singular zeal may be the greater, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have proven, and daily doe prove the most pernicious and dangerous enemies of the true Religion: against this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41505:3"/>generation, which saith, <hi>Let us deal wisely with them,</hi> we have this comfort and advantage, that we know amongst all the Enemies of the Truth they least of all think that they doe GOD service.</p>
            <p>We who are intrusted for the time, to be the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners of the late Generall assembly, sitting at Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh for the Affaires of the Kirk committed to our care and diligence, specially for preserving of our own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and Peace against all sorts of Enemies, and according to the interest of this Kirk for Unitie in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Uniformitie of Government with the Kirk of England, which was no new motion of ours, but a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position made by the Commissioners of the Treaty, which then received from the Kings Majestie and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of England, such an Answer as hath been the ground of many Consultations, Declarations and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Letters since, and of a renewed supplication at this time to the Kings Majestie, and of a Declaration to the Parliament of England for the same effect. While we are thus exercised, we are desired by some Noblemen, Barons and Burgesses, occasionally met at Edinburgh, to send some of our number to joyne with them in a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, representing to the right Honourable the Lords and other Commissioners of Parliament for the conservation of peace, their humble thoughts and fears that the print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of His Majesties Letter of the date, <hi>December</hi> 5. by Warrand and Command of the right Honourable the Lords of His Majesties Privie Councell, and the not printing of the Declaration of both Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, unto which the printed Letter was an Answer, might be taken by the Kingdome of England, as an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the whole matter, and all the particulars which it did expresse, and thereby to animate and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke this Nation against them as Rebells and Traitours;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41505:3"/>We finding that the Petition did homologate both in the end and meanes with our Commission, and the matter of our present deliberations, did willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly satisfie the desire of the Petitioners, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from our tender and dutifull respect to His Majesties Honour, for preventing and removing of all occasion of jealousies and suspitions betwixt the two Kingdomes, for preservation both of our own peace at home, and our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon peace with England, and for promoving the so much desired Unitie of Religion, a meane of all other most conducing to the conservation of both, did with them (conforme to the order observed in such cases since the beginning of our late Reformation) humbly supplicate, that the meaning of the publication of His Majesties Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter might be cleared, and that the Declaration of both Houses of Parliament to their Bretheren of Scotland might be printed and published, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But behold! after a few dayes a contrary Petition is presented to the Lords of His Majesties Privie Councell, by some private Noblemen, Barons and Gentlemen, which coming to our hands, we found after due exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to be nothing else but a secret plot and subtle un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-mining of all the present designes of this Kirk and Kingdome, for Unitie of Religion, and of all the work of God in this Land: And therefore we made upon it the observations and animadversions following.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> That private Persons knowing that the Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners of the Generall Assembly were sitting at this time about such matters as they meddle with in their Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that we had joined in presenting a Petition to the Commissioners for conserving of Peace, much about the same particulars, whereof they could not be ignorant by reason of the Act of the late Assembly, they did not so much as acquaint us with their intentions, that we might
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41505:4"/>either have petitioned with them, or have advised them to desist: which although it may seem to be but an errour in the manner of their doing, yet doth it imply contempt, usurpation and division; and being winked at, may be the cause of much disturbance and confusion in these times, especially they professing that they desire to cleare themselves and their intentions, not only to the Lords of Councell, but to the Kings Majestie, to the Kingdome of England, and to all the world, which is nothing else but under the colour of a Petition to make a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Declaration, contrary to the proceedings, not only of the Generall Assembly and their Commissioners, but also to the desires and diligence of the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Treaty of the honourable Lords of Councell, and of the Conservators of Peace, who have all concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and do still concurre in their joint desires of Unitie of Religion in His Majesties Dominions, resolving to presse this Unitie to the uttermost of their endeavours as a necessary preservative of our own Reformation and Peace, which without it cannot long subsist; and much crossing that clause of our Covenant wherein we sweare, that we shall not cast in any lett or impediment that may stay or hinder any such resolution, as by common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent shall be found to conduce for so good ends.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Although the Petitioners professe with us that they desire the Union of this Iland in Religion and Kirk-Government, yet their Petition doth too plainly and palpably tend to the contrary, as is apparent by this three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold consideration: 1. For remedie of the divisions and distractions in England, the Petition desireth only <hi>the suppression of insolent Papists, malignant schismaticks, and disloyall Brownists and Separatists, the speciall, if not sole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movers and fomenters of these unhappy mis-understandings:</hi> and thus doth passe by the Prelates, and balketh the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41505:4"/>Bishops, who have been the most restlesse sticklars in this businesse, and the prime authors of all these tragedies since the beginning, and thereby would take us off our right and straight course of pressing uniformitie in Kirk government in the Treaty, in our Declarations, and in the Generall assembly: The Apologists for the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would have reduced the Prelates either to Papists, or to Sectaries; but the Authors of the Petition intended better service, by sending the Petition to England, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trenching upon the Lordly Prelacie, or touching the Prelates at all; which from strangers is an high provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against the Kingdome and Parliament of England, and no small prejudice against the proceedings of this Kirk and Kingdome for Reformation. 2. This Petition doth indirectly cast foule aspersions upon these who are most zealous for the Reformation in England, and doth very much sumbolize with the language of the Popish and Prelaticall party in England; calling the Parliament, and all that seek after Reformation, <hi>Brownists, Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, Authors of tumultuary conventions,</hi> &amp;c. 3 It hint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at our zeal and forwardnesse in the matter of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Kirk of England: which may appear thus; The Petitioners declare, <hi>That since the duty of charity doth oblige all Christians to pray and professe their desires, that all others were of the same Religion with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore they represent their wishes for uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Religion and Kirk government, as an expression and testimony of their affection to the good of their brethren in England: Declaring further, That <hi>they desire this work to be prosecuted without presuming or usurping to prescribe lawes and rules of Reformation to their Neighbours.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain they repeat, that <hi>by their wishes and desires they intend no wayes to passe their bounds, in prescribing or setting downe rules and limits to His Majestie and Houses of Parliament
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41505:5"/>their wisedome and authoritie, in the way of prosecution hereof.</hi> And why do they so plentifully purge, and carefully clear themselves concerning this particular, if their intention were not to leave some aspersion upon this Kirk and State, as if we were passing our bounds, by presuming to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe rules and limits to His Majestie and Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament? For further evidence whereof, it is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, that in the first part of their Petition they plainly professe, that they are clearing themselves and their intentions, lest they should be thought to be invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with us in the same desires, judgements, and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: So that all which they say by way of clearing of themselves and their intentions, ariseth from this ground, that they will not be thought involved with us in our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, judgements, and opinions, and so condemne us in these particulars, in which chiefly they justifie themselves: neither can we knit together their words, or interpret their apologie to another meaning. Now what is this else but to overturne the very foundation of all our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for this work of Reformation, which was the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Treaty for union in Religion, and uniformity in Kirk government? Not as a matter nakedly desired and wished for; but as a principall demand, and necessary mean, without which neither truth nor peace could be secured unto us. The importance and necessity whereof hath been since that time so deeply laid to heart by this Kirk and Kingdome, that as the Generall Assembly, and we for our part representing the same, so the Lords of Councell, and the Commissioners of Parliament for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of the peace, concurring with us, have been, and are most serious and solicitous in the importunate and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest pressing of this union in Religion and Kirk govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, resolving to use our uttermost endeavours in the prosecuting and effectuating of such a blessed and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41505:5"/>necessary work, as being dearer to us then all our Lives and Fortunes: neither did the Generall Assembly spare to represent their humble advice concerning the way of prosecuting that work to the houses of Parliament, and to others seeking after Reformation in England.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Their Petition doth tend to a dangerous division in this Kirk and Kingdome; for as it doth reflect upon us for our joining in the Petition concerning His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties printed Letter presented to the Commissioners of Parliament, for conservation of the Peace, upon a pretext (as it saith) of the not sitting of the Privie Councell at that time; so it insinuateth, that we did presume to questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or seek of the Lords of Councell an account of their Actions; both which are foule and groundlesse aspersions: yea, it declareth, that the Petitioners doe so far dislike our Petition, that they conceive they were wanting in their dutie and allegiance to the Kings Majesty, if by their si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence they should suffer themselves to be involved with us in the like desires, judgements and opinions: thus plainly professing a division and separation, aswell from us, as from other Noblemen, Gentlemen, Burgesses and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, here occasionally met, with whom we joyned in the foresaid Petition. And not content to with-draw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from being involved with us, the Petition doth also insinuate, that in their opinion we are involved in the breach of dutie and allegiance to the Kings Majestie; and not we only, but the Commissioners for conserving the Peace, who did hearken and assent to our Petition, and did seriously recommend to the Lords of His Majesties Privie Councell, that part of the Petition which did concerne their Lordships clearing of their meaning in the publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of His Majesties Letter, by their causing print the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Parliament of England. The Lords of Councell are likewise involved in the same breach of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeance,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41505:6"/>legeance, by reason of their grant of our desire in causing print the Declaration of both Houses of Parliament, upon the warrant of another Letter from His Majesty, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with declaring, that their Lordships publication of any Paper, doth not import their approbation of the contents thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> The Petition above-mentioned doth import no small prejudice to the happy Union and late Treaty of Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Kingdomes, insinuating to the Lords of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Privie Councell, that their Lordships in answering our Petition concerning the clearing of their meaning in the publication of His Majesties Letter, might do no act which may give His Majesty occasion to repent him of that trust for aid and assistance, which He was pleased to declare in his Letter December 5. that he reposeth in us His Subjects of this His ancient and native Kingdome; whereby the Petitioners do intimate their desires, that the Lords of Councell might not declare that for which we did supplicate, but to declare by their not printing the Declaration of the Parliament, that their Lordships pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of His Majesties Letter did import their approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the contents thereof, and so acknowledge their willingnesse to take Arms against the Parliament of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, upon the grounds contained in that Letter, when His Majesty shall require them so to doe. And for their own part they declare, that they think themselves obliged <hi>in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very cause which may concerne His Majesties honour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with their friends and followers in quiet manner, or in Arms, as they shall be required of his Majestie, his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, or any having his authoritie.</hi> Which if understood and applyed aright, no loyall Subject can deny, but it is meant and expressed in their Petition, as in opposition to our Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition; So in contemplation of the Differences betwixt His Majesty, and the Parliament of England, unto which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41505:6"/>their words relate. For they professe to represent such particulars as they are confident will much conduce to the removing of all the mistakes betwixt His Majesty, and the Parliament: of which particulars, that is the first, That ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to His Majesties trust expressed in His Letter De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember 5. the Subjects of this Kingdome declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves willing and ready to take Armes in every cause which may concerne His Majesties honour, being requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by His Majesty, or any having His Authoritie. And is not this to make void the Treaty, ratified by the publick Faith of this Kingdome, and Act of Parliament, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging all taking up of Armes against the Kingdome or Subjects of England, upon any pretence whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, without consent of Parliament, declaring the breach of Peace; and that after three moneths warning? Which treaty the Estates of Parliament did swear to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve inviolably, in the same very oath in which they did swearallegeance to the Kings Majestie; thereby declaring, that the observation of the conclusions of the treaty may well consist with our duty and allegeance to our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, whereas the Petition doth indirectly put some aspersion of Laesmajestie upon the Parliament for confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and swearing to observe the Articles of the Treatie, which in the opinion of the Petitioners are inconsistent with our oath of allegeance. If they say that their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did only insinuate that we may not take armes to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist the Parliament against the King, they put upon it a sense which it cannot beare, both because they knew that the supplication of the Noblemen, Barons, and others assisted by us, did not directly nor indirectly containe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such thing, And because His Majesties trust expressed in that Letter (which they desire His Majestie may not have occasion from us to repent) is not only a negative trust, that we will not take armes against him, but a posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41505:7"/>trust and confidence, that we will be ready to assist him. And finally, because the clause of the Supplication of the Generall Assembly which they mention as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining our obligation to our Soveraigne, and that in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the present distractions in England, is positive, and not negative.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> Lastly, the Petitioners for their own private ends doe very much wrest and mis-apply our Nationall Covenant, about which the whole Nation and all the Members of the Kirk of Scotland have as great reason, as by the mind of man can he conceived, to be most tender and cautelous; and which every one amongst us, according to his place and calling, is obliged to vindicate from every violation; and namely, from sinister glosses, and false interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which may be the fountaine and cause (the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant being one principall rule of our actions and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings) of many scruples, transgressions, and disturban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. We acknowledge before God, and professe before the World, that by our Covenant we are bound to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of our power, with our meanes and lives, to stand to the defence of our dread Soveraigne the Kings Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, his Person and Authoritie, in the defence and preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the true Religion, Lawes and Liberties of this Kirk and Kingdome; likewise in every cause which may concerne his Majesties honour, according to the Lawes of this Kingdome, and the duty of good subjects, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with our friends and followers in quiet manner, and in armes, as we shall be required of His Majestie, his Councell, or any having his authoritie. We know, that he who wilfully transgresseth one Article of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, it being copulative, is by interpretation guiltie of all. And therefore under the greatest paines expressed in the Covenant, we resolve for our selves, all the dayes of our lives, and doe exhort all others to that duty which they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41505:7"/>have sworne and subscribed to perform to the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie: But we desire to know of the Petitioners, who are so ready at this time to make their own conclusions out of the Covenant, which was never intended by it, nor thought upon at the first or last time at the swearing and subscribing thereof, how it comech to passe that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver took the Covenant in their mouth, but in this one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle? Are they not bound by their Covenant, and the same clause of the supplication, cited by them, to their mutuall concurrence and assistance for the cause of Religion? and to stand, with their means &amp; lives, to the defence thereof, in the doctrine and discipline of the Kirk of Scotland? and to live godly, soberly, &amp; righteously in this present world? True Conscience of duty and sincerity in keeping the Covenant, will make the obedience universall. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, seeing the Petitioners would only have unitie in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and uniformitie in Kirk-Government advanced by Christian wishes and fair meanes, and yet insinuateth their offer by armes to decide the municipall debates of England, anent Civill matters, while the Civill and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastick Judicatories, and the rest of this Kirk and Kingdome are desiring an Assembly, and a Parliament, to consider their interest and duty, and to contribute their best endeavours (in what is above the power of their Commissioners) to further this unitie of Religion, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move these distractions in England, we ask, whether they presume that they alone keep the Covenant, and would render unto Christ which is Christs, and unto Cesar which is Cesars, and that all others are Covenant-brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers? Thirdly, do they not know that the Covenant was subscribed in the years, 1581. and 1591. before King <hi>James</hi> was King of England? and that in the particular Heads and Articles, it is qualified by expresse limitations and restrictions to this <hi>Kirk and Kingdome, to the Religion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41505:8"/>Lawes and Liberties of Scotland?</hi> therefore can no more be extended to municipall debates, and to the Lawes and Liberties of England, unto which we are strangers, then the Kingdome of England can judge of our Lawes, and determine our differences, the two Kingdomes being still independent, &amp; not subordinate one to another but pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell, which is more at large expressed in the beginning of the treaty of Peace: Nor is the sending of our Forces into Ireland a necessary duty of our Covenant, but a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary testimony of our high respects to our King, and of our brotherly kindnesse to the Kingdome of England, as was expressed by the estates in the last Parliament. Fourthly, do not the Petitioners observe the limitations expresly contained in the words cited by themselves, <hi>according to the Lawes of this Kingdome and duty of good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects?</hi> which some of them may remember was interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Assembly, as if it had been said within this Kingdome; nor was there ever any law of this Kingdome of further extent: A law and Treaty there is, we know, forbidding it. Fifthly, may they not learne from the printed Letter, that the Kings Majestie expresseth not his confidence of assistance from Scotland, upon any ground or article of the Covenant, which His Majestie knoweth to be so obligatory amongst us, but from the obedience, duty and affection of His Subjects of Scotland, without any mention of our Covenant? But such is the superero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of some of the Petitioners above what His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie requires, that they will put a tye of the Covenant upon us, where GOD and the King hath left us free. Thus have we related the interpretation of the Covenant made by the Assembly, and vindicate that clause of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which is so far perverted by this Petition.</p>
            <p>The Petitioners hearing that their Petition had given offence to the Commissioners of the Assembly, and that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41505:8"/>we were about the examination and censuring thereof, did direct foure of their number with another Petition to give satisfaction to the exceptions that might be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, as is contained in their Remonstrance which they exhibite for that end: But when in a calme and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et conference, all the particular reasons above-written, were represented unto them, and all means used to move them to part from their Petition, they could not be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, neither in the name of others that had sent them, nor for themselves, to acknowledge the smallest errour ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the matter of their Petition, or in the manner of their petitioning; only they made offer to joyn with us the Commissioners of the Assembly in a new Petition for Unitie or Religion, and gave such glosses and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations upon the clauses of their Petition, which were most excepted against, as could neither consist with the words nor scope of the contrivers and authors. And therefore being desired and earnestly dealt with, they not only refused to declare under their hands that no other thing was meant in the Petition, then they had by word expressed, but also did shun to allow or permit us, the Commissioners of the Assembly, to declare so much in their names, as was contained in their own verball expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, intending that the Petition should go through this and the neighbouring Kingdomes for the ends for which it was devised, and especially into England, for frustrating all that hath been done, or is now in doing by this Kirk and Kingdome, out of their pious intention, and by their publick endeavours for unitie of Religion, and the peace of the two Kingdomes: And in the mean time that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing should be extant from them or their confessions and interpretations in the contrary.</p>
            <p>In this case we judge it necessary, and finde it incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent to us to emit this Declaration, for vindicating our
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41505:9"/>present and by-past proceedings: for our silence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivence were a breach of our dutie to GOD, a neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the charge and trust committed unto us by the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Assembly, an occasion as well of divisions at home, as of jealousies and mis-understandings betwixt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, a confirmation of the Petitioners in their errour, &amp; an indirect approbation of their petition; as likewise a cause of stumbling and doubting to others who shall read or hear of such a Petition, especially to those, who through want of discerning, are not able to prove things that are different, might be easily deceived by their pretexts and sophistications. We are not ignorant that this Petition doth very much reflect upon the Parliament, Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and the Conservators of Peace; but this we leave to the wise consideration of these civill Judicatories, as they shall finde themselves concerned: we have contained our selves within our proper Spheare, not daring to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect our own duty, while wee forbeare to meddle with that which pertaines to others.</p>
            <p>The Petitioners are not all of one kinde and dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of heart, but are unequally yoked against the Work of God. Some of them are known, and some of them have been conceived to be Malignants and Incendiaries from the beginning: but God forbid that they should now by opposing unitie in Religion and Peace, prove enemies to all Religion and Righteousnesse; for then will it be both thought and spoken, that all this time past they have been lying in wait for the season, when their malignancie might appear; and it will be observed, that they who were of late at distance amongst themselves, are now at agreement; and that like <hi>Samsons</hi> foxes, they turn taile to taile with fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands in the midst, to burn up the husbandrie of GOD, when now the fields are white for the harvest. It cannot be the cause of God which is not either secretly or openly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41505:9"/>opposed by men of perverse mindes; nor can blinded mindes and hardened hearts, till God touch them by his power, choose but secretly or openly oppose the truth and cause of God. And therefore it is very necessary that such men take heed unto themselves, lest by their fulnesse of all subtletie and mischief, and their not ceasing to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the right wayes of the Lord, they bee found to bee fighting against God, which will prove bitternesse in the end: Others there be who have joyned in this Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (to judge charitably) not from opposition to the unitie of Religion, they having done and suffered so much, and hazarded all for the Reformation of Religion at home, but partly out of unwillingnesse to refuse or displease their friends to whom they are obliged by natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or other particular bands, and partly by reason of the specious pretences in the Petition, not considering the bad intentions of the contrivers, or the dangerous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance and consequence of the Petition it self: Let such men, to whom the Commissioners of the Assembly wish all true happinesse, seriously think as well upon the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the work, and the quality of the company with whom they joyne, as upon their own intentions, lest they wrong both themselves, and the cause of God, contrary to their desires, and more then they are aware of; and let them remember how dangerous it is to walke in the counsell of the ungodly, for their soules to come into their secret, and their glory to be joyned with their Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. If counsell be like the principall agent, consent is like the instrument; and to be instruments of, or accessorie unto the hinderance of the intended, and so much desired unitie of Religion, which maketh so fair a way for the Kingdome of Christ through the Earth, how great a sin is it? and how great a sorrow shall it be?</p>
            <p>All this we have thought good to expresse concerning
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41505:10"/>that divisive Petition, and those who are joyned together in it, being cast in our way as a stumbling block and rock of offence, for hinderance of the work of God, both at home and abroad. And as we exhort and warne all the People of God in this Land to observe them who cause divisions and offences, and to avoid them; So we hope assuredly, that no such courses, nor counsells shall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper, as do tend directly or indirectly, to the stopping of the course of the Gospel, or to the suppression of Religion and Reformation, and that God Almighty shall against all impediments carry forward this his blessed and glorious Work, to the glory of his great Name, to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdome of his Son Jesus Christ, to the destruction of Antichrist, to the firme Peace and happy Union of all His Majesties Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Religion, and to His Majesties Honour and Happinesse: Whom GOD preserve to raign long and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously over us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:41505:10"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>At <hi>Edinburgh</hi>
                  <date>the eighteenth day of <hi>January,</hi> 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Commissioners appointed by the Kings Majestie, and his Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for conserving the Articles of the Treaty, Doe finde that the Petition given in to his Majesties Privie Councell by some Noblemen and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men upon the <hi>10.</hi> of this moneth, doth tend to the hinderance of their proceedings and endeavours in this publick Work commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them by the Kings Majesty, and Parliament: And that it is prejudiciall to the authority of this Commission, the same being in opposition of what was that day recommended by the saids Commissioners to the Councell. And ordaine this Act to be published for stopping all farther progresse of that or other Petitions of that kinde, And that it be printed with the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Commissioners of the Generall Assembly made here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anent.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sic subscribitur<lb/>
                  <hi>Arch. Primerose</hi> Cler. Commiss.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>